TWINKLE JAIN

Boston, MA \displays 857.707.8421 \display jain.t@northeastern.edu \displayslinkdein.com/in/jaintwinkle \displayslinkdein.com

SUMMARY

Current research aims to develop application-transparent strategies for optimizing utilization of limited resources in distributed environments that encompass both compute-centric and data-centric platforms. Key projects include: a) a low-overhead checkpoint-restart architecture for CUDA; b) an assessment of existing speculative execution for detecting and handling straggler tasks in Spark; and c) an analysis of the role of heartbeat arrival in straggler detection in Hadoop.

EDUCATION

Northeastern University, Boston, MA

Fall 2016 - Present

Ph.D. in Computer Science (switched from MS in Fall 2017)

(GPA: 3.7/4.0)

Thesis advisor: Prof. Gene Cooperman

Relevant Courses: Computer Systems, Algorithms, Virtualization, Compiler

Jai Narain Vyas University, Jodhpur, India

Aug 2012 - Oct 2015

Master of Computer Applications, First Class with Distinction

(equivalent GPA: 3.9/4.0)

Relevant Courses: Algorithms, Data Structures, Computer Architecture, Operating Systems

WORK EXPERIENCE

Northeastern University Graduate Research Assistant Sep 2016 - Present

Boston, MA

• **Projects**: Fix single point of failure of the ROS master, CRAC: a split-process-based architecture to checkpoint CUDA applications, CRAC-M: a flexible split-process design to support multiple lower halves (CUDA and MPI).

Teaching Assistant Boston, MA

• Computer Systems (CS 5600) in Fall 2022 and Intensive Computer Systems (CS 7600) in Spring 2021 and Spring 2023,

MemVerge, Inc.

May - Aug 2022

Research Intern (Remote)

San Francisco, CA

- Developed and maintained MANA, an MPI-Agnostic Network Agnostic checkpoint-restart tool for MPI applications.
- Troubleshot memory corruption-related issues in MANA to support at least three scientific HPC applications contributing 25% of the total machine hours at National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERSC) sites.

IBM TJ Watson Research Center

Jun - Aug 2021

Research Intern (Remote)

Yorktown Heights, NY

- Analyzed existing resiliency support and proposed an improved framework in Ray, a distributed execution platform.
- Demonstrated a 5% improvement in runtime; averted crashes caused by memory overflow via configuration tuning.

Inria

 $May - Jul \ 2019 \ \& \ Feb - Aug \ 2020$

Research Visitor

Nantes, France

- Evaluated and improved speculative execution implementation (to detect and handle stragglers) in Hadoop and Spark.
- Published findings across multiple conference papers (see publication section).

Mentor Graphics

May – Aug 2018

System Engineer Intern

Waltham, MA

• Developed a Distributed Multi-Threaded CheckPointing (DMTCP) plugin to restart an optimized checkpointed build as a debug build; reduced time taken in debugging an in-house large-scale application by 90% (see patent).

Stratus Technologies

May - Aug 2017

Platform Engineer Intern

Maynard, MA

• Assessed performance of COarse-grained LOck-stepping (COLO) technique on QEMU for fault-tolerance in servers.

SELECTED ACADEMIC PROJECTS

Northeastern University

Compiler for a small Programming Language

Sep - Dec 2018

• Built a standard compiler in SML-NJ language for Andrew Appel's Tiger programming language in a team of two.

Decrease Down-time in Live Process Migration

Nov - Dec 2016

• Decreased downtime by 80% in process migration from one host to another by prioritizing memory-pages sending order.

Jai Narain Vyas University

Maze Traversing Robot

Oct 2014 – Jan 2015

• Designed and built a wireless, camera-driven robot that identifies the path in a maze. Programmed a micro-controller to communicate via an RF module for navigation input (see Pixelate award).

AWARDS

- Represented Northeastern University and Khoury College of Computer Sciences at the 2019 Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing conference.
- Led team of four; 3rd place among 33 teams in "Pixelate" at Techfest 2015, Bombay (Asia's Largest Technical Festival).
- Won four 1st-place and three 2nd-place awards at state-level technical events at Encarta 2013, Jodhpur, Rajasthan.

PATENT

Software Checkpoint-Restoration between distinctly compiled executables Twinkle Jain, Vipul Kulshrestha, Kenneth W. Crouch (US11429379B2)

(Granted in Aug 2022) Mentor Graphics

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Full Papers

- "Towards an effective Speculative Execution in Spark," **T. Jain** and S. Ibrahim (under review). (VLDB 2023)
- "On the (In)Accuracy of Stragglers Detection in Hadoop," T. Lambert, T. Jain, and S. Ibrahim. (FGCS 2023)
- "CRAC: checkpoint-restart architecture for CUDA with streams and UVM," **T. Jain** and G. Cooperman (https://dl.acm.org/doi/pdf/10.5555/3433701.3433803). (SC 2020)

Short Papers

- "Stragglers' Detection in Big Data Analytic Systems: The Impact of Heartbeat Arrival," T. Lambert, S. Ibrahim, T. Jain and D. Guyon (https://doi.org/10.1109/CCGrid54584.2022.00084). (CCGrid 2022)
- "Checkpointing SPAdes for Metagenome Assembly: Transparency versus Performance in Production," **T. Jain** and J. Wang (https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2103.03311). (SuperCheck 2021)

Posters/Presentations

• Stragglers Detection in Big Data Analytic Systems: The Impact of Heartbeat Arrival

(CCGrid 2022)

• Checkpoint/Restart of MPI applications over the Cray GNI Network via Proxies

(MUG 2018)

• DMTCP: Fixing the single point of failure of the ROS master

(ROSCon 2017)

ADDITIONAL RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Invited Talks

- MANA/CRAC: A Preprocessor for Safe Transparent Checkpointing of MPI and CUDA (EuroMPI/USA 2022)
- C/R Requirements for CUDA Applications at NERSC (Checkpoint/Restart Requirements Gathering Workshop 2022)

Reviewer

- Program committee member and reviewer for SuperCheck 2021, SuperCheck-SC 2021, and SuperCheck-SC 2022.
- Reviewer for IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA) 2021 and High Performance Computing (HiPC) 2020.

TECHNICAL KNOWLEDGE

Languages and APIs: C/C++ (CUDA/MPI/POSIX), Python (numpy/matplotlib/pandas).

Distributed Frameworks: SLURM, Hadoop, Spark, Yarn, HDFS. **Deployment Tools:** Kubernetes, OpenShift, Docker.

Tools: GDB, Git, Tmux, Shell, LATEX, VS Code.